A Guide to the Records of the Virginia Pupil Placement Board, 1957-1966
Library of Virginia
- Series VI. Applications, 1959-1966., Extent: 224.35 cu. ft. (641 boxes). (Box 87-728)
  - Subseries II. Routine, 1957-1966., 217.7 cu. ft. (413 boxes) (Box 106-728)
    - Waynesboro (N-Z) - Williamsburg-James City County - Winchester, 1964-1966. (Box 728)
  - Subseries III. Public School Registration, 1960-1964., 4 cu. ft. (4 Boxes)
    This subseries contains Richmond City Public School registrations forms, the forms contains students name, address, a vaccinations record, parents names and occupations, as well as, current and prior schools. These education records have been restricted and are to remain sealed for 75 years from their date of creation in accordance with the Family Education Rights and Privacy Act (FERPA) and Codes of Virginia 2.2-3705.4 and 2.2-3705.1
    This subseries is arranged alphabetically by student's last name.
    - Richmond City (A - J), 1960-1962. (Box 729)
    - Richmond City (K - Z), 1960-1962. (Box 730)
    - Richmond City (A - K), 1962-1964. (Box 731)
    - Richmond City (L - Z), 1962-1964. (Box 732)
- Series V. Printed Materials, 1957-1960., Extent: 13 cu. ft. (4.55 boxes). (Box 733-746)
  - Subseries I. Publications, 1957-1966., 1.4 cu. ft. (4 boxes) (Box 733-736)
    This subseries consists of published materials collected by the board, such as, briefs, directories, magazine articles and public school laws.
    This subseries is arranged alphabetically
    - Brief - U.S. Court of Appeals (Thurgood Marshall, Council, 8054), 1959. (Box 733, Folder 1)
    - Brief - U.S. Court of Appeals, Arlington (7310), 1957. (Box 733, Folder 2)
    - Brief - U.S. Court of Appeals, Arlington (887), 1958. (Box 733, Folder 3)
    - Brief - U.S. Court of Appeals, Charlottesville (7303), undated. (Box 733, Folder 4)
    - Brief - U.S. Court of Appeals, Fairfax County (4753), 1957. (Box 733, Folder 5)
    - Brief - U.S. Court of Appeals, Frederick County (9193), 1963. (Box 733, Folder 6)
    - Brief - U.S. Court of Appeals, Greene County (9325), 1964. (Box 733, Folder 7)
    - Brief - U.S. Court of Appeals, Hopewell (9258), 1960-1963. (Box 733, Folder 8)
    - Brief - U.S. Court of Appeals, Lynchburg (8722), 1962. (Box 733, Folder 9)
    - Brief - U.S. Court of Appeals, Newport News (7430), 1957. (Box 733, Folder 10)
    - Brief - U.S. Court of Appeals, Powhatan County (8944), 1962-1963. (Box 733, Folder 11)
    - Brief - U.S. Court of Appeals, Richmond (9471), 1961-1963. (Box 733, Folder 12)
    - Brief - U.S. Court of Appeals, Richmond (8757), 1962. (Box 733, Folder 13)
    - Brief - U.S. Court of Appeals, Roanoke (8534), 1962. (Box 734, Folder 1)
    - Brief - U.S. Court of Appeals, Roanoke County (8535), 1962. (Box 734, Folder 2)
    - Brief - U.S. District Court, Savannah, Georgia, 1963. (Box 734, Folder 3)
    - Catalog of Standardized Tests, 1961. (Box 734, Folder 4)
    - Commission on Civil Rights - Reports, 1961-1962. (Box 734, Folder 5)
    - Commission on Civil Rights - Transcript, 1961-1962. (Box 734, Folder 6)
    - Commission on Education, 1959. (Box 734, Folder 7)
    - Directory - Fauquier County, 1964-1965. (Box 734, Folder 8)
    - Directory - Petersburg Public Schools, 1960-1961. (Box 734, Folder 9)
    - Directory - Richmond Public Schools, 1961-1965. (Box 735, Folder 1)
    - Directory - Scott County, 1961-1962. (Box 735, Folder 2)
    - Directory - State Board of Education, 1957-1962. (Box 735, Folder 3)
    - Directory - State Board of Education, 1963-1966. (Box 735, Folder 4)
    - Directory - Virginia Postal Zones, 1961/1963. (Box 735, Folder 5)
    - General Assembly, 1956-1960. (Box 735, Folder 6)
    - International Association for the Advancement of Ethnology and Eugenics, Inc., 1960-1963. (Box 735, Folder 7)
    - Legislation - Pupil Placement Laws, Undated. (Box 735, Folder 8)
    - Look Magazine - "The Negro Now", 1965 Mar 23. (Box 735, Folder 9)
    - Manual of the Senate and House of Delegates, 1962. (Box 736, Folder 1)
    - Miscellaneous, 1962-1964. (Box 736, Folder 2)
    - Other State's Placement Laws, 1955-1961. (Box 736, Folder 3)
    - Propoganda Literature, 1958-1964. (Box 736, Folder 4)
    - The Saturday Evening Post - "Harlem: The Black Jungle", 1964 June 13. (Box 736, Folder 5)
    - U.S. Department of Health, Education and Welfare, 1962/1965. (Box 736, Folder 6)
    - Newsletter - Virginia Civil War Commission, 1963-1965. (Box 736, Folder 7)
    - Virginia Commission on Constitutional Government, 1959-1963. (Box 736, Folder 8)
    - Virginia School Laws, 1958-1960. (Box 736, Folder 9)
  - Subseries II. Newspapers Clippings, 1957-1966., 9 boxes (3.15 cu. ft.) (Box 737-746)
    This subseries contains newspaper clippings which were collected by the board from papers throughout Virginia, with a large percentage of materials being taken from the Richmond Times Dispatch, Richmond News Leader, and the Freelance Star. Most articles are labled as to which newspaper and on what date the article was published. The clippings are grouped by date not publication, the majority of articles make some reference to the Pupil Placement Board, with the relevant information often being underlined. Other common topics include virginia schools, desgregation, protests, federal court rulings, Dr. Martin Luther king, Freedom Riders, Little Rock, and the NAACP.
    The bulk of the clippings from 1958 are in regard to desegregation in Little Rock, or the struggles of Arlington and Norfolk. Many articles also refer to the DeFebio case, in which a white mother refused to sign the placement applications for her two sons resulting in the children being denied admitance to public school, the case eventually reached the United States Court of Appeals (brief 4753 can be found in box ? folder 5). Articles from March of 1960 followed the resignation of the original Pupil Placement Board, and the resulting appointments of new members in July. 1966 contains articles relating to increased integration throughout the state, not only schools but in the work place as well as, the actions of Health, Education, and Welfare (HEW) are also covered.
    This collection is arranged Chronologically.
    - 1957 Jan-July. (Box 737)
    - 1957 Aug-1958 Feb. (Box 738)
    - 1958 Mar-Aug. (Box 739)
    - 1958 Sept-1959 Apr. (Box 740)
    - 1959 May - 1962 Sept. (Box 741)
    - 1962 Oct - 1963 June. (Box 742)
    - 1963 July-1964 Feb. (Box 743)
    - 1964 Mar-Aug. (Box 744)
    - 1964 Sept-1965. (Box 745)
    - 1966. (Box 746)